<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="handler" status="Unproofed">
    <title>Routing and Handlers</title>
    <intro>
        <p id="intro1">If we look at Yesod as a Model-View-Controller framework, routing and handlers make up the controller. For contrast, let's describe two other routing approaches used in other web development environments:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>Dispatch based on file name. This is how PHP and ASP work, for example.</li>
            <li>Have a centralized routing function that parses routes based on regular expressions. Django and Rails follow this approach.</li>
        </ul>
        <p id="intro2">Yesod is closer in principle to the latter technique. Even so, there are significant differences. Instead of using regular expressions, Yesod matches on pieces of a route. Instead of having a one-way route-to-handler mapping, Yesod has an intermediate data type (called the route datatype, or a type-safe URL) and creates two-way conversion functions.</p>
        <p id="intro3">Coding this more advanced system manually is tedious and error prone. Therefore, Yesod relies heavily on Template Haskell and Quasi-Quotation to automatically generate this code for you. This chapter will explain the syntax of the routing declarations, give you a glimpse of what code is generated for you, and explain the interaction between routing and handler functions.</p>
    </intro>
    <section id="route-syntax">
        <title>Route Syntax</title>
        <section id="pieces">
            <title>Pieces</title>

            <p id="pieces1">The first thing Yesod does when it gets a request (well, maybe
                not the <i>first</i>) is split up the requested path into
                pieces. The pieces are simply tokenized at all forward slashes.
                So:</p>

            <codeblock>toPieces "/" = []
toPieces "/foo/bar/baz/" = ["foo", "bar", "baz", ""]</codeblock>

            <p id="pieces2">You may notice that there are some funny things going on with
                trailing slashes, or double slashes ("/foo//bar//"), or a few
                other things. Yesod believes in having <term>canonical
                    URLs</term>; if someone requests a URL with a trailing
                slash, or with a double slash, they automatically get a
                redirect to the canonical version. This follows the RESTful
                principle of one URL for one resource, and can help with your
                search rankings.</p>

            <p id="pieces3">What this means for you is that you needn't concern yourself
                with the exact structure of your URLs: you can safely think
                about pieces of a path, and Yesod automatically handles
                intercalating the slashes and escaping problematic
                characters.</p>

            <p id="pieces4">If, by the way, you want more fine-tuned control of how paths
                are split into pieces and joined together again, you'll want to
                look at the cleanPath and joinPath methods in the <link
                    chapter="yesod-typeclass" section="join-path">Yesod
                    typeclass</link> chapter.</p>
            <section id="types-of-pieces">
                <title>Types of Pieces</title>
                <p id="pieces5">When you are declaring your routes, you have three types of pieces at your disposal:</p>
                <defs>
                    <def term="Static">This is a plain string that must be matched against precisely in the URL.</def>
                    <def term="Dynamic single">This is a single piece (ie, between two forward slashes), but can be a user-submitted value. This is the primary method of receiving extra user input on a page request. These pieces begin with a hash (#) and are followed by a data type. The datatype must be an instance of <code>SinglePiece</code>.</def>
                    <def term="Dynamic multi">The same as before, but can receive multiple pieces of the URL. This must always be the last piece in a resource pattern. It is specified by an asterisk (*) followed by a datatype, which must be an instance of <code>MultiPiece</code>. Multi pieces are not as common as the other two, though they are very important for implementing features like static trees representing file structure or wikis with arbitrary hierarchies.</def>
                </defs>
                <p id="pieces6">Let us take a look at some standard kinds of resource patterns you may want to write. Starting simply, the root of an application will just be <code>/</code>. Similarly, you may want to place your FAQ at <code>/page/faq</code>.</p>
                <p id="pieces7">Now let's say you are going to write a Fibonacci website. You may construct your URLs like <code>/fib/#Int</code>. But there's a slight problem with this: we do not want to allow negative numbers or zero to be passed into our application. Fortunately, the type system can protect us:</p>
                <snippet name="handler-fibs"/>
                <p id="pieces8">On line 1 we define a simple newtype wrapper around Int to protect ourselves from invalid input. We can see that SinglePiece is a typeclass with two methods. <code>toSinglePiece</code> does nothing more than convert to a <code>String</code>. <code>fromSinglePiece</code> <i>attempts</i> to convert a <code>String</code> to our datatype, giving an error message when this conversion is impossible. By using this datatype, we can ensure that our handler function is only ever given natural numbers, allowing us to once again use the type system to battle the boundary issue.</p>
                <!-- FIXME new release of web-routes-quasi that does away with the Either? -->
                <advanced><p id="pieces9">In case you are wondering, the parse error messages returned by <code>fromSinglePiece</code> are not ever shown by Yesod. This all has to do with some decisions made in the design of <hackage>web-routes</hackage>. However, all of that is outside of the scope of this book.</p></advanced>
                <p id="pieces10">Defining a MultiPiece is just as simple. Let's say we want to have a Wiki with at least two levels of hierarchy; we might define a datatype such as:</p>
                <snippet name="handler-wiki"/>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section id="resource-name">
            <title>Resource name</title>

            <p id="rn1">Each resource pattern also has a name associated with it. That
                name will become the constructor for the <term>type safe
                    URL</term> datatype associated with your application.
                Therefore, it has to start with a capital letter. By
                convention, these resource names all end with a capital R.
                There is nothing forcing you to do this, it is just
                common practice.</p>

            <p id="rn2">The exact definition of our constructor depends upon the
                resource pattern it is attached to. Whatever datatypes are
                included in single and multi pieces of the pattern become
                arguments to the datatype. This gives us a 1-to-1
                correspondence between our type safe URL values and valid URLs
                in our application.</p>

            <advanced><p id="rn3">This doesn't necessarily mean that <i>every</i> value
                    is a working page, just that it is is a potentially valid
                    URL. As an example, that value <code>PersonR
                        "Michael"</code> may not resolve to a valid page if
                    there is no Michael in the database.</p></advanced>

            <p id="rn4">Let's get some real examples going here. If you had the resource
                patterns <code>/person/#String</code> named
                <code>PersonR</code>, <code>/year/#Int</code> named
                <code>YearR</code> and <code>/page/faq</code> named
                <code>FaqR</code>, you would end up with a route data type
                roughly looking like:</p>

            <codeblock>data MyRoute = PersonR String
             | YearR Int
             | FaqR</codeblock>

             <p id="rn5">If a user requests the relative URL of
                 <code>/year/2009</code>, Yesod will convert it into the value
                 <code>YearR 2009</code>. <code>/person/Michael</code> becomes
                 <code>PersonR "Michael"</code> and <code>/page/faq</code>
                 becomes <code>FaqR</code>. On the other hand,
                 <code>/year/two-thousand-nine</code>,
                 <code>/person/michael/snoyman</code> and
                 <code>/page/FAQ</code> would all result in 404 errors without
                 ever seeing your code.</p>

             <advanced><p id="rn6">Throughout the above discussion, I used the terms type-safe URLs and routes datatype interchangeably. Don't be confused, they are the exact same thing. They just sound better in different contexts.</p></advanced>
         </section>
         <section id="handler-spec">
             <title>Handler specification</title>

             <p id="rn7">The last piece of the puzzle when declaring your resources is how they will be handled. There are three options in Yesod:</p>
             <ul>
                 <li>You have a single handler function which should be used for all request methods.</li>
                 <li>You want to write a separate handler function for each request method you will support. All other request method will generate a 405 Bad Method response.</li>
                 <li>You want to pass off to a <term>subsite</term>.</li>
             </ul>

             <p id="rn8">The first two are very easily specified. A single handler
                 function will be a line with just a resource pattern and the
                 resource name, such as <code>/page/faq FaqR</code>. In this
                 case, the handler function must be named
                 <code>handleFaqR</code>.</p>

             <p id="rn9">A separate handler for each request method will be the same,
                 plus a list of request methods. The request methods must be
                 ALL CAPITAL LETTERS. For example, <code>/person/#String
                     PersonR GET POST DELETE</code>. In this case, you would
                 need to define the three handler functions
                 <code>getPersonR</code>, <code>postPersonR</code> and
                 <code>deletePersonR</code>.</p>

             <p id="rn10">Subsites are a very useful&#x2014; but complicated&#x2014; topic in Yesod. We
                 will <link chapter="subsite">cover writing subsites
                     later</link>, but using them is not too difficult. The
                 most commonly used subsite is the static subsite, which serves
                 static files for your application. In order to serve static
                 files from <code>/static</code>, you would need a resource
                 line like:</p>

             <codeblock>/static StaticR Static getStatic</codeblock>

             <p id="rn11">In this line, <code>/static</code> just says where in your URL
                 structure to serve the static files from. There is nothing
                 magical about the word static, you could easily replace it
                 with <code>/my/non-dynamic/files</code>.</p>

             <p id="rn12">The next word, StaticR, gives the resource name. The next two
                 words are what specify that we are using a subsite.
                 <code>Static</code> is the name of the <term>subsite
                     foundation datatype</term>, and <code>getStatic</code> is
                 a function that gets a <code>Static</code> value from a value
                 of your main application's foundation datatype.</p>

             <p id="rn13">Let's not get too caught up in the details of subsites now. We
                 will look more closely at the static subsite in the <link
                     chapter="scaffold">scaffolded site chapter</link>.</p>

         </section>
    </section>
    <section id="dispatch">
        <title>Dispatch</title>
        <p id="dispatch1">Once you have specified your routes, Yesod will take care of all the pesky details of dispatch for you. You just need to make sure to provide the appropriate <term>handler functions</term>. For subsite routes, you do not need to write any handler functions, but you do for the other two. We mentioned the naming rules above (MyHandlerR GET -&gt; getMyHandlerR, MyOtherHandlerR -&gt; handleMyOtherHandlerR). Now we need the type signature.</p>
        <section id="dispatch-return-type">
            <title>Return Type</title>
            <p id="dispatch2">Let's look at a simple handler function:</p>
            <snippet name="handler-simple"/>
            <p id="dispatch3">Look at the type signature of getHomeR. Unfortunately, there is a lot of complexity here to dig through. We will cover the GHandler monad in <link chapter="handler" section="ghandler">more detail later</link>. Next come <code>subsite</code> and <code>Simple</code>. This is where we need to start heading down the rabbit hole...</p>
            <p id="dispatch4">The same way your application has a <term>foundation</term> datatype and associated <term>type-safe URL</term> datatype, so does every subsite. As an example, the Static subsite's foundation datatype has information on how to look up a requested file. The Authentication subsite has a URL datatype that provides login, logout and various other actions.</p>
            <p id="dispatch5">The GHandler monad needs information on both the current subsite and current master site. Most of the time, <i>these are the same</i>! When you are writing your typical handler functions, you only have a single foundation going on. So in the code snippet above, the type signature for getHomeR could also have been <code>GHandler Simple Simple RepHtml</code> without any problems.</p>
            <p id="dispatch6">For now, just accept it as a strange quirk that you need to deal with this extra type parameter. In fact, it is recommended to use a type synonym like <code>type Handler = GHandler MyApp MyApp</code> at the beginning of your code (the <link chapter="scaffold">scaffolded site</link> does this for you). And when we get to the <link chapter="subsite">subsite chapter</link> we will explore why this awkwardness is a necessity, and the huge benefits we reap as a result.</p>
            <section id="chooserep">
                <title>ChooseRep</title>

                <p id="chooserep1">That just leaves us one thing: <code>RepHtml</code>. When we
                    <link chapter="rest" section="representations">discuss
                        representations</link> we will explore the <i>why</i> of
                    things more; for now, we are just interested in the
                    <i>how</i>.</p>

                <p id="chooserep2">As you might guess, RepHtml is a datatype for HTML responses.
                    But as you also may guess, web sites need to return responses
                    besides HTML. CSS, Javascript, images, XML are all necessities
                    of a website. Therefore, the return  value of a handler
                    function can be any instance of <code>HasReps</code>.</p>

                <p id="chooserep3">HasReps is a powerful concept that allows Yesod to automatically
                    choose the correct representation of your data based on the
                    client request. For now, we will focus just on simple instances
                    such as RepHtml, which only provide one representation.</p>

            </section>
        </section>

        <section id="arguments">
            <title>Arguments</title>

            <p id="arguments1">But not every route is as simple as the HomeR we just defined.
                Take for instance our PersonR route from earlier. The name of
                the person needs to be passed to the handler function. This
                translation is very straight-forward, and hopefully intuitive.
                For example:</p>

            <snippet name="handler-args"/>

            <p id="arguments2">The arguments have the types of the dynamic pieces for each route, in the order specified. Also, notice how we are able to use both <code>RepHtml</code> and <code>RepPlain</code>.</p>

        </section>

    </section>
    <section id="ghandler">
        <title>The GHandler Monad</title>
        <p id="ghandler1">The vast majority of code you write in Yesod sits in the GHandler monad. If you are approaching this from an <abbr title="Model-View-Controller">MVC</abbr> background, your GHandler code is the Controller. Some important points to know about GHandler:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>It is an instance of <code>MonadIO</code>, so you can run any IO action in your handlers with <code>liftIO</code>. By the way, <code>liftIO</code> is exported by the <code>Yesod</code> module for your convenience.</li>
            <li>GHandler is really a <term>monad transformer stack</term> providing a number of different components.</li>
            <li>A Reader component provides access to immutable information about a request and the environment: the foundation value, request headers and much more.</li>
            <li>A Writer component allows you to add extra response headers.</li>
            <li>A State component deals with session variables, allowing them to be both read, written and deleted. Sessions are discussed in <link chapter="sessions">their own chapter</link>.</li>
            <li>An Error component deals with <term>short-circuiting</term>. Despite the name, these are not necessarily errors: you can use this for sending static files and redirecting in addition to sending error responses.</li>
        </ul>

        <advanced>

            <p id="ghandler1a">And on top of all this, there is in fact a
                larger generalization from GHandler: a GGHandler. While a
                GHandler wraps around an Iteratee, which allows it to read the
                request body, a GGHandler can wrap around any monad, including
                directly around IO. This generalization is necessary for
                dealing with catching exceptions. We will discuss this on more
                depth later. <!-- FIXME add link --></p>

        </advanced>

            <p id="ghandler2">The remainder of this chapter will give a brief introduction to some of the most common functions living in the GHandler monad. I am specifically <i>not</i> covering any of the session functions; that will be addressed in the <link chapter="sessions">sessions chapter</link>.</p>
        <section id="application-info">
            <title>Application Information</title>
            <p id="ghandler3">There are a number of functions that return information about your application as a whole, and give no information about individual requests. Some of these are:</p>
            <defs>
                <def term="getYesod">Returns your applicaton foundation value. If you store configuration values in your foundation, you will probably end up using this function a lot.</def>
                <def term="getYesodSub">Get the subsite foundation value. Unless you are working in a subsite, this will return the same value as <code>getYesod</code>.</def>
                <def term="getUrlRender">Returns the <term>URL rendering function</term>, which converts a type-safe URL into a <code>String</code>. Most of the time- like with Hamlet- Yesod calls this function for you, but you may occassionally need to call it directly.</def>
                <def term="getUrlRenderParams">A variant of <code>getUrlRender</code> that converts both a type-safe URL and a list of query-string parameters. This function handles all percent-encoding necessary.</def>
            </defs>
        </section>
        <section id="request-info">
            <title>Request Information</title>
            <p id="ghandler4">The most common information you will want to get about the current request is the requested path, the query string parameters and POSTed form data. The first of those is dealt with in the routing, as described above. The other two are best dealt with using the <link chapter="forms">forms module</link>.</p>
            <p id="ghandler5">That said, you will sometimes need to get the data in a more raw format. For this purpose, Yesod exposes the <code>Request</code> datatype along with the <code>getRequest</code> function to retrieve it. This gives you access to the full list of GET parameters, cookies, and preferred languages. There are some convenient functions to make these lookups easier, such as <code>lookupGetParam</code>, <code>lookupCookie</code> and <code>languages</code>. For raw access to the POST parameters, you should use <code>runRequest</code>.</p>
            <p id="ghandler6">If you need even more raw data, like request headers, you can use <code>waiRequest</code> to access the <link chapter="wai">WAI</link> request value.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="short-circuiting">
            <title>Short Circuiting</title>
            <p id="ghandler7">The following functions immediately end execution of a handler function and return a result to the user.</p>
            <defs>
                <def term="redirect">Sends a redirect response to the user. You can specify whether you want a 301, 302 or 303 status code. This function takes a type-safe URL as a destination. There are also <code>redirectString</code> and <code>redirecParams</code> variants.</def>
                <def term="notFound">Return a 404 response. This can be useful if a user requests a database value that doesn't exist.</def>
                <def term="permissionDenied">Return a 403 response with a specific error message.</def>
                <def term="invalidArgs">A 400 response with a list of invalid arguments.</def>
                <def term="sendFile">Sends a file from the filesystem with a specified content type. This is the preferred way to send static files, since the underlying WAI handler may be able to optimize this to a <code>sendfile</code> system call. Using <code>readFile</code> for sending static files should not be necessary.</def>
                <def term="sendResponse">Send a normal HasReps response with a 200 status code. This is really just a convenience for when you need to break out of some deeply nested code with an immediate response.</def>
            </defs>
        </section>
        <section id="headers">
            <title>Response Headers</title>
            <defs>
                <def term="setCookie">Set a cookie on the client. Instead of taking an expiration date, this function takes a cookie duration in minutes. Remember, you won't see this cookie using <code>lookupCookie</code> until the <i>following</i> request.</def>
                <def term="deleteCookie">Tells the client to remove a cookie. Once again, <code>lookupCookie</code> will not reflect this change until the next request.</def>
                <def term="setHeader">Set an arbitrary response header.</def>
                <def term="setLanguage">Set the preferred user language, which will show up in the result of the <code>languages</code> function.</def>
                <def term="cacheSeconds">Set a Cache-Control header to indicate how many seconds this response can be cached. This can be particularly useful if you are using <xref href="http://www.varnish-cache.org/">varnish on your server</xref>.</def>
                <def term="neverExpires">Set the Expires header to the year 2037. You can use this with content which should never expire, such as when the request path has a hash value associated with it.</def>
                <def term="alreadyExpired">Sets the Expires header to the past.</def>
                <def term="expiresAt">Sets the Expires header to the specified date/time.</def>
            </defs>
        </section>
    </section>
    <summary>
        <p id="summary1">Routing and dispatch is arguably the core of Yesod: it is from here that our type-safe URLs are defined, and the majority of our code is written within the GHandler monad. This chapter covered some of the most important and central concepts of Yesod, so it is important that you properly digest it.</p>
        <p id="summary2">This chapter also hinted at a number of more complex Yesod topics that we will be covering later. But you should be able to write some very sophisticated web applications with just the knowledge you have learned up until here.</p>
    </summary>
</chapter>
