<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="migrate6to7" status="Unproofed">
    <title>Migration Guide: 0.6 to 0.7</title>
    <intro>
        <p id="i1">The following is a migration guide from Yesod 0.6.* to Yesod 0.7.0. These
            are notes I took while performing the migration on the Haskellers.com website.
            It may not be completely exhaustive, but it should be a good start.</p>

        <p id="i2">If you run into issues which are not addressed here, please
            add a comment on this paragraph so that I can update the article
            and others can see what's missing.</p>
    </intro>
    <section id="no-warnings">
        <title>No Warnings</title>
        <p id="nw1">Before you get started, I recommend you get your current
            code to compile without any warnings. That way, as you begin
            migrating, you'll know that any new warnings are caused by the
            migration process itself. In fact, you may even want to turn on
            <code>-Wall -Werror</code> in your cabal file.</p> </section>
    <section id="install-yesod">
        <title>Install yesod</title>
        <p id="iy1">In theory, this will simply require running <code>cabal
                update &amp;&amp; cabal install yesod</code>. In practice,
            cabal may not be able to figure everything out for you. If you run
            into <xref
                href="http://cdsmith.wordpress.com/2011/01/16/haskells-own-dll-hell/">DLL
                hell</xref>, the simplest solution currently is to just delete
            your .ghc folder.</p>

    </section>
    <section id="cabal">
        <title>Update cabal file</title>
        <p id="c1">Almost all underlying packages for Yesod have been upgraded,
            including WAI, Hamlet, etc. Make sure to include newer versions.
            For the most part, if you depend on the yesod package itself, you
            can leave off version bounds on underlying packages. However, cabal
            may not always do the right thing.</p>
        <p id="c2">Some specific notes:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>Obviously, make sure your version bounds on the yesod package allow 0.7.0. I recommend <code>&gt;= 0.7 &amp;&amp; &lt; 0.8</code></li>
            <li>wai-extra no longer provides SimpleServer. Instead, you should use Warp.</li>
            <li>Make sure to add a -threaded GHC option when compiling all executables, even devel-server.</li>
        </ul>
        <p id="c3">Make sure to run <code>cabal install</code> to automatically
            install any dependencies. If you run into DLL hell here, then
            (surprise) an easy solution is to wipe out .ghc and run <code>cabal
                install</code> again.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="hamlet">
        <title>Update your Hamlet templates</title>
        <p id="h1">Hamlet 0.7 introduces major syntax changes to all three
            template languages (Hamlet, Cassius and Julius). It also includes a
            utility that will automatically convert your files to the new
            syntax. The following commands will overwrite your current <!-- FIXME make this bold, why won't it work? bug in xml-enumerator methinks -->
                files, so make sure you've backed up/committed first:</p>
        <codeblock>hamlet6to7 *.hs
hamlet6to7 Handler/*.hs
hamlet6to7 hamlet/*.hamlet
hamlet6to7 cassius/*.cassius
hamlet6to7 julius/*.julius</codeblock>
          <p id="h2">Unfortunately the tool gives a lot of false positives about mismatches in Hamlet. My best advice is to look at the diffs: this will simultaneously give you good confidence that the conversion worked correctly and get you familiar with the new syntax.</p>
      </section>
      <section id="cabal-install">
          <title>cabal install</title>
          <p id="ci1">Even though your code won't build yet, this will be a
              good way to see if you've set up your cabal file correctly. One
              common error you'll encounter is that many of the modules that
              used to be in the yesod package are now included in separate
              packages, such as Yesod.Helpers.Static now living in
              yesod-static. Make sure to add in any missing packages to your
              cabal file. Some likely offenders will be:</p>
          <ul>
              <li>warp</li>
              <li>yesod-form</li>
              <li>yesod-newsfeed</li>
              <li>yesod-static</li>
              <li>Possibly need to move some dependencies (like ToHtml typeclass) from hamlet to blaze-html</li>
              <li>Control.Monad.Invert is no longer used; instead, use relevant modules from the monad-peel package (most likely Control.Exception.Peel).</li>
          </ul>
      </section>
      <section id="instances">
          <title>Show, Read and Eq for Html</title>

          <p id="in1">Hamlet is now using blaze-html's Html datatype. While I
              think this is a good move overall, one downside is that
              blaze-html does not provide Show, Read and Eq instances of Html.
              When you include an Html value in a Persistent model, it won't be
              able to create those instances by default. If you get error
              messages, just add a single "deriving" line at the bottom. For
              example:</p>

          <codeblock>Person
  name String
  bio Html
</codeblock>
          <p id="in2">becomes</p>

  <codeblock>Person
  name String
  bio Html
  deriving
</codeblock>
        </section>
        <section id="peel">
            <title>MonadInvertIO to MonadPeelIO</title>
            <p id="p1">Nuff said :)</p>
        </section>
        <section id="urlRenderOverride">
            <title>urlRenderOverride</title>
            <p id="uro1">The previous scaffolded version of urlRenderOverride no longer works. Use this one instead:</p>
  <codeblock>urlRenderOverride a (StaticR s) =
    Just $ uncurry (joinPath a Settings.staticroot) $ renderRoute s
urlRenderOverride _ _ = Nothing</codeblock>
        </section>
        <section id="runDB">
            <title>runDB: need liftIOHandler</title>
            <p id="rdb1">For the impatient: stick <code>liftIOHandler</code> at the beginning of runDB like so: <code>runDB db = liftIOHandler $ fmap connPool getYesod &gt;&gt;= Settings.runConnectionPool db</code></p>

            <p id="rdb2">For everyone else: WAI 0.2 contained the request body as an Enumerator in the Request datatype, and an Application was <code>Request -&gt; IO Response</code>. In WAI 0.3, an Application is <code>Request -&gt; Iteratee ByteString IO Response</code>. Long story short: all code in your Handler function now lives on top of an Iteratee monad so that it can access the request body.</p>

            <p id="rdb3">This works great most of the time. The only downside is when you need to deal with exceptions. It's impossible to define a MonadPeelIO instance for Iteratee. Therefore, in Yesod 0.7, we have a new datatype called GGHandler, which is just a generalization of GHandler to allow an arbitrary inner monad.</p>

            <p id="rdb4">GHandler defaults to having an Iteratee on the inside. But when you need a MonadPeelIO (like we do in Persistent), you need to have an IO on the inside. Eventually though, you'll need to convert your <code>GGHandler IO</code> to a <code>GHandler</code>. That's what <code>liftIOHandler</code> does.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="mime-mail-part">
            <title>mime-mail Part constructor</title>
            <p id="mmp1">mime-mail introduced a new record to the Part constructor- called partHeaders- that did not exist before. To get the same behavior as before, just pass in an empty list. This is especially relevant for users of yesod-auth's email plugin.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="newsfeed">
            <title>Feed, formerly known as AtomFeed</title>

            <p id="newsfeed1">Patrick Brisbin has become a co-maintainer on the yesod-newsfeed
                package, and added a feature I'm sure many people will
                appreciate: RSS feed support. The best part is that it uses the
                same datatype as the Atom feeds, so with just a few changes you
                can have both versions of newsfeed:</p>

            <ul>
                <li>Change AtomFeed to Feed</li>
                <li>Change AtomFeedEntry to FeedEntry</li>
                <li>Change records like atomTitle to feedTitle</li>
                <li>Add two new records: feedDescription and feedLanguage</li>
                <li>Change RepAtom to RepAtomRss</li>
                <li>Change atomFeed to newsFeed</li>
                <li>Change imported module to Yesod.Helpers.Feed</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section id="static">
            <title>fileLookupDir no more</title>
            <p id="static1">The standard line for getting static file serving previously was
    <code>s = fileLookupDir Settings.staticdir typeByExt</code>. In Yesod 0.7, we're migrating to the much more powerful yesod-app-static package. The replacement for the above line is <code>s = static Settings.staticdir</code>.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="mptc">
            <title>MultiParamTypeClasses</title>
            <p id="mptc1">A major new feature is the simplification of the dispatch code. While this almost entirely is transparent to the user, one user-visible changes is the unification of YesodSite and YesodSubSite into YesodDispatch. As a result, your Controller.hs file will now need MultiParamTypeClasses turned on.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="stobs">
            <title>String to ByteString</title>
            <p id="stobs1">In a few places (redirectString, mime-type) I've replaced Strings with ByteStrings. I'm not 100% certain this was the right choice, but it <i>is</i> more correct in the sense that these values are sent verbatim across the wire. A simple Data.ByteString.Char8.pack will get you the old behavior.</p>
        </section>
    </chapter>
